Docker can be installed on all OS whether it is Windows, Linux or Mac OS, we will
understand the installation process on each of these OS. Go to Docker.com where you can
download the Docker desktop application and this application is available for every operating
system whether it is Mac based on Apple silicon chip or Intel chip, Windows based on AMD 64
chip or ARM 64 chip and Linux. So let us first understand the process for installing
Docker desktop on Linux. Here in this page you go to Ubuntu and these are the two commands
which you have to run on the terminal process the pseudo app dash get update and second
is these pseudo app dash get install dot slash Docker dash desktop dash AMD 64 dot
depth. This will download the depth package and install it on your Linux computer. After
it is installed you need to launch your Docker desktop through this system CTL command,
run it on your terminal and you will start the Docker desktop. Now understand the
process of other two whether it is Mac OS or Windows you just download this package
and install it. I am using Windows 11 based on AMD chip. So I need to download this version
and download has started and it will take some 1 to 2 minutes to complete in the meanwhile
we can learn what is WSL known as Windows subsystems for Linux. Windows subsystem for Linux
WSL it is a feature of Windows that allows you to run a full Linux environment including
command like tools like bash and applications directly on Windows without a virtual machine.
There are two ways to install WSL first is do it manually by yourself and second is by
letting Docker desktop to install WSL for you. We will prefer the second option we now
learn how to install WSL manually head on to Google and type in install WSL and click
on this Microsoft result here you get the commands to install WSL for example WSL install
and WSL.exe install and WSL.exe list online so you have to run these commands on the
command prompt window. So let's open command prompt window and we now copy this command
that will list all these Linux installation packages so we can install WSL copy paste and
type in you want to and then you enter it to install it. I will not install WSL instead
let Docker desktop do this for me so in the command prompt let me show you one more command
if I type in WSL and you can see this message Windows subsystems or Linux has no installed
distribution this means my PC has no WSL right now but don't worry once I installed Docker
desktop WSL will be installed for me by Docker desktop so let's continue with the installation
of Docker desktop application Docker desktop is now downloaded we open the folder which
is redown loads folder and double click it to start the installation procedure and we
can see the installation has started click okay and we have to wait some 5 minutes for the
Docker desktop to get installed on our laptop so it's nearing completion and it has installed
click okay and now we open the Docker desktop from the start menu and once it is open
you will find it in the task bar so okay it has started click accept and in this screen
just skip and now it is starting and we can see it has started and since there are no container
containers we are not seeing any containers or images or volumes right now we will be creating
them one more thing I want to show you in the Docker desktop here click settings and click
on resources and then go to WSL integration here you will see all the Linux restores WSL
which you have installed manually we did not install any one manually and so we are not
seeing any of them if we would have installed it then we would have the option to select
them for Docker desktop to use them so in our case Docker has already installed WSL
and we are using it before we move forward let us quickly see some container commands number
one is docker ps this will list all the containers in your local machine second one is
docker create name of the container and then name of the image so this will create a container
with a given image and name of this container will be this one first and docker start container
name this will start the container by the name of this one docker stop container name this
will stop the container whose name is this one then we have docker run my image this command
will run a container with a given image name so my image you replace it with this image
name and docker will run a container with this image on it docker run dash p these are the 2 ports
this is the image which will run and docker will create a container for this image and first
is the host port and second is the container port the traffic from the host port which
will be on local machine will be forwarded to 80 80 of the container so you will be opening
local host column 5000 and this will go straight away to this container port 80 80 we will
see more about it when we will create our home dotnet app in a container next command
this docker rm test c this will delete this container by the name of test c docker container
prune this will delete all the containers that are not running this will free of your local
machine space and docker logs this one this is the container id you can see the logs of
the container whose id is this one by this command then there are the docker image commands
docker image ls this will list all the images in your local machine similarly the other
command is docker build dash team my image dash f docker file dot this will build the image
by the name of my image and bit the docker file which is residing on the current location
so building image command from this based on docker file you use this command similarly
this is the same command but it has a colon b1 which is the tag images can have any tag
like v1 version 1 version 2 latest etc you can give the image any tag when you are creating
the image docker pull hello world this will pull the hello world docker image from docker
hub into your local laptop or local machine so that you can use it locally another command
this docker push my image this will push my image to the docker repository docker hub so
you can store my image to docker hub repository online so that other people can use it
docker image rm hello world this will remove the image by the name hello dash world so
you replace hello dash world with the image name and it will delete the image on your
docker machine and docker image prune this will remove all the images that are not currently
used in a container so this will similar it this will delete the images so that you get
these spaces so let's continue with the development of .NET app in a docker container